
<rss version="2.0"
    xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Trepix</title>
        <link>https://trepix.io/</link>
        <description>Recent content on Trepix</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 19:15:35 +0100</lastBuildDate>
        
            <atom:link href="https://trepix.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        
        
            <item>
                <title>Statement of intention</title>
                <link>https://trepix.io/blog/statement-of-intention/</link>
                <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 19:15:35 +0100</pubDate>
                
                <guid>https://trepix.io/blog/statement-of-intention/</guid>
                <content>&lt;p&gt;After getting over the first little detail of having a website, here we are writing the first post. I wanted to believe that writing wasn&amp;rsquo;t as difficult as it seemed, but here&amp;rsquo;s the reality to smash our face again.
So I will try to be brief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the first and &lt;strong&gt;most important&lt;/strong&gt; disclaimer before going in about the whys of this blog is that everything I&amp;rsquo;m going to write here is just my experience, my learning and opinions. And don&amp;rsquo;t forget that opinions are like farts: everyone farts, everyone likes their own and other&amp;rsquo;s farts are usually unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first objective that I want to hit, is to improve my knowledge retention. Over the last years, I&amp;rsquo;ve read a lot of books but nowadays I can only retain a few core ideas and sometimes others just ring me a bell and I have to look them up. As opposed, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that I&amp;rsquo;ve internalized better coding techniques like refactoring or TDD because I practiced them, again and again. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to try summarizing each book in order to retain the core information. Probably I will read fewer books, but let&amp;rsquo;s see if I have a higher ROI of my time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is &lt;strong&gt;maybe&lt;/strong&gt; helping another lost traveler like me. This road is long, not always easy and certainly not clear. Probably, I will not share useful learnings for everyone (nor do I pretend it) but maybe someone who&amp;rsquo;s some steps behind could find something useful. If you find something helpful here don&amp;rsquo;t forget to share with others what you learned (the knowledge, not my blog).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last reason to write this blog is to improve my English, so I hope will have enough energy to write some posts in English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope you find something useful every once in a while. And don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to share your opinion!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: Kudos to Anna for help me with my English 😘&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
                <description>After getting over the first little detail of having a website, here we are writing the first post. I wanted to believe that writing wasn&amp;rsquo;t as difficult as it seemed, but here&amp;rsquo;s the reality to smash our face again. So I will try to be brief.
Well, the first and most important disclaimer before going in about the whys of this blog is that everything I&amp;rsquo;m going to write here is just my experience, my learning and opinions.</description>
            </item>
        
  </channel>
</rss>